It shouldn't be that complicated to
carry out simple edits in a speech corpus.
And luckily with databaseExplorer
it isn't.
Learn how to inspect edit,
and save your files
all with just some simple clicks
of your mouse.
Often, speech
researchers need to handle
a large number of audio files,
and although most steps in your research
plan can be fully automated,
sometimes there is no sleek
and efficient option
other than to manually check your files
one by one.
With databaseExplorer, it is easy to look
through a folder of audio files,
cut your desired part,
and save it to a new location.
databaseExplorer is a PRAAT
plugin, meaning you must have PRAAT already
installed on your computer to use it.
If this is not the case, as always,
check out the official website of PRAAT
where you will find
all the information you need.
The link is in the description.
Installing the tool is simple.
Just go to our GitHub website.
Locate the databaseExplorer folder
and click on Download as zip.
Once downloaded and extracted,
you'll notice
that there are two scripts in the folder.
If you'd like to add a button
to your objects window to open database
Explorer more comfortably, you can open
the installation script and run it.
This will create a copy of the database
Explorer script in your PRAAT preferences
directory, and add a button
to your Dynamic Objects window, meaning
you will only see the button once you
selected a sound in the objects window.
If you don't wish to install the button,
you can simply open databaseExplorer
by running the script
called databaseExplorer manually.
To start
databaseExplorer, you need to first load
one of the audio files in the folder
you'd like to look through into your PRAAT
Objects window.
Then select the file and open databaseExplorer.
This will open a window
showing you the waveform and spectrogram
of the currently selected sound.
In your folder.
On the left side of the screen,
you can see a list of the other audio
files in the folder, and how many files
come before and after the selected file.
On the right side of your screen,
there is a legend showing you
how to use the plugin.
Let's go through the functions one by one.
The first three lines tell you
how to select a portion of the sound
and cut away the rest.
Simply click into the waveform
at the point you want your new file
to begin.
Click once more
where you want the file to end.
If you missed, just click a third time
and both selections are removed.
Next up.
When you press the spacebar,
the plugin will save the audio
with the changes
you made to your write directory.
You can choose the write directory
by pressing the W key.
This will open a finder window
in which you can choose the location.
Your files should be saved
to press the D key to delete a file
already saved in your write directory.
The next five lines tell you how to move
through the files in your folder.
You can use the left and right
arrow keys to move one file up or down.
Pressing the spacebar will also move
you one forward.
However, it will also always save the file
to your right directory.
If you want to make bigger jumps.
You can use the up and down arrow to jump
three files up and down in your folder.
If that's too fancy for you,
or if your folder contains many files,
you can press the G key and manually type
in the file number you want to jump to.
Press the P key
to listen to the currently selected sound.
“Die Frau des Apothekers weiss immer was Sie will.”
with the plus and minus keys
You can increase and decrease
the filter bandwidth of your spectrogram.
This can be useful when you're looking
for specific Formants in your sound.
If you have a textgrid file, then
it can be displayed by pressing the T key.
This is a toggle meaning.
By pressing T again,
the textgrid disappears.
Note that the textgrid and audio file
must have identical file
names for this feature to work.
By pressing the S
key, you can display the settings window.
It lets you choose whether instead
of saving your modified files,
it should save the originals.
If you select this option,
the modifications you made will show up
in an interval tier saved in a textgrid file together with your sound.
If you do this while you have the textgrid selected,
databseExplorer will simply combine
your textgrid with the new modifications,
losing no data.
You can also either turn on or off
the function to move on with the spacebar.
This way, when you save a file,
you will have to manually move on
with the arrow keys afterwards.
Additionally,
it is possible to change the frequency
ceiling of the displayed spectrogram.
This is especially helpful
when audio has information
in frequency bands
above the default 8000Hz.
Finally, when you're done, pat yourself
on the back and press the Q key
to exit the application. Well done.
That's it for this video.
I hope you learned something
and that you had fun.
If you think we missed something
or want to write us, go to our website
where you will find all the information
on who we are, what we do,
and how to get in touch with us.
This was Clemens
from the LiRI Resource Hub.
Keep on exploring
and I hope you have a great day.